Hello everyone
大家好
Today I will introduce to you: OEM metapackages and Concourse CI
今天來跟大家介紹一下 OEM metapackages 跟 Concourse CI
This presentation can be found in the following URL
這個投影片可以在下面這個網址看到
First, I will introduce myself
首先我是誰
I am FourDollars
我是FourDollars，然後我是 Debian Developer、Ubuntu 跟 Gnome 的 Member
Uh, I am also an employee in Canonical, and also a Vim fantic
呃 我也是 Canonical 的員工，然後也是 Vim 使用者
I usually use Plurk as my main social network
我自己本身比較多使用的 social network 是 Plurk
Okay, let’s get down to business~
好 那我們來進入正題囉～
What are OEM metapackages?
什麼是 OEM metapackages
There is an article on the Open Source news
在 Open Source 的新聞上面有這一篇文章
and there is also an announcement in our Ubuntu Mailing concerning this topic
然後在我們的 Ubuntu Mailing List 也有這個 Announce
So this is basically saying that we (Canonical) has certified OEM machines
那這個就是在介紹，我們 Canonical 有針對有 certified 過的 OEM 機器
There will be different OEM certified experience (regarding different platform)
然後會有一些不一樣的 OEM certified 的 experience
The operational details is explained in the article of this mailing list
然後他的一些運作的細節會在這個 Mailing List 的文章裡面解釋
Okay
好
Simply put,
那簡單來說就是
We will provide an OEM metapackage for the platform
我們會對那個 platform
The platform could be an All-in-one PC,
Maybe 是一個 All-in-one 的 PC
a laptop, or a desktop
或者是一個 laptop 的電腦，或者是桌上型的電腦
And then have them to use the kernel that we specified
提供一個 OEM metapackage， 然後來使用我們所指定的 kernel
So as you can see in the picture below
那大家可以看到下面這個圖
We provide two different kernels for Ubuntu 20.04 LTS
我們在 Ubuntu 20.04 LTS 提供了兩種不同的 kernel
One is the OEM kernel, and the other is the generic HWE kernel
那一個是 OEM kernel，然後另外一個是 generic 的 HWE kernel
And...
然後就是....
Our OEM metapackage will mainly use the upper kernel
我們 OEM metapackage 他主要會去使用上面這個 kernel
Why would we use the above one?
那為什麼會去使用上面的 kernel？
Of course it's because that,
當然就是因為
The machines we use are newer machines
我們這些在 enable 的這些機器
The hardware will be relatively newer, so it will need latest kernel drivers to support it
他會是比較新的硬體，所以他會需要一些比較新的 kernel driver 來支援他
So we introduced this workflow
於是我們就設計出了這樣的方式
We will have two different kernels simultaneously
就是我們同時會有兩個不一樣的 kernel
OEM kernel will equipped with newer version of linux kernel
OEM kernel 會使用比較新的 linux kernel 版本
It's basically like this
大概就是醬
Here, the generic SWE below will use a more stable version
那這邊，下面這邊的 generic SWE 就會使用比較穩定的版本
Then you can also see that at some point here, version 5.4 will directly switch to the newer version 5.8
然後大家也可以看到，這邊的切換就是 5.4 到某一個時間點之後，就會直接切換到比較新的 5.8
Also, we switched from kernel version 5.8 to 5.11 this month
那在這個月剛好也是直接從 5.8 的 kernel 直接切換到 5.11
It will have a direct conversion
他會有一個直接的轉換
There is something different in OEM kernel. It will have some overlapping time
那  OEM kernel 這邊會不太 一樣的是：他會有一些重疊的時間
For example, the time period of Linux kernel 5.6
像那個....Linux 5.6 的 kernel 他的時間就是
You see, there's a long overlap with the 20.04b OEM kernel down here.
你看，他跟下面這個 20.04b 的 OEM kernel，他有一些蠻長的重疊的時間
Until I think June of 2021
一直到了這個大概是六月的時候，今年六月的時候
It then finally switched from 5.6 to 5.10
他才從 5.6 整個轉換到 5.10
Later on, we got a new OEM kernel version 5.13 in July
同時我們在七月的時候，有一個新的 OEM kernel，他的 5.13 也就出現了
In the future, the OEM kernel version 5.10 will switch to 5.13
那像這個 5.10 的這個 OEM kernel，他之後就會轉換到 5.13
It's roughly like that
大概就是這樣子
The main idea of OEM metapackage is that
那我們 OEM metapackage 主要就是說
you get to install these newer version of Linux OEM kernel earlier
讓你去再早一點去安裝到這些 Linux OEM 的 kernel
Install a relatively new version of the kernel to support some relatively new hardware
就是裝到比較新的 kernel，來支援 一些比較新的硬體
Then how do we achieve this?
那他是怎麼辦到的呢？
There are two main points
他主要就是有兩點
One is that we use modaliases to match the hardware
一個是：他使用 modaliases 去 match 這個硬體
The other is that it will use Ubuntu driver, ubiquity and update-manager to install OEM meta
然後另外是：他會使用到 Ubuntu driver、ubiquity 跟 update-manager 來安裝 OEM meta
So what are modaliases?
那什麼是 modaliases？
modaliases is a file system provided by the kernel
modaliases 就是一個 file system，kernel 提供的 file system
The ArchWiki has a pretty clear explanation about this
那 Arch 的 wiki 上面有蠻清楚的解釋
It is actually an interface provided by the kernel
他其實就是一個 kernel 提供的 system..... 一個 interface
And you can obtain hardware information there
然後你就可以從那邊去得到硬體的一些資訊
The following command can help you find those files directly
那下面這個指令就是說你可以直接找到那些檔案
Then you can read the contents of the file directly
然後就可以直接把檔案內容，把他讀出來
You can get to know what modaliases look like
你就知道 modaliases 長得怎麼樣子
A more practical example is provided below
下面這邊有提供一個比較實際的例子
Ubuntu driver is used to install drivers for additional hardware
Ubuntu driver 是用來安裝一些額外的硬體所需要的驅動程式
Here is the ubuntu-drivers list
像這邊就是 ubuntu-drivers list
It shows that "Hey, I have an Nvidia driver 460 and Nvidia driver 470."
他就會列出說，欸我這邊有可以提供 Nvidia driver 460 跟 Nvidia driver 470
Then we can use the command: ubuntu-drivers devices to see that
那我們可以再利用：ubuntu-drivers devices 這個指令來看
Oh, it matched to this file
哦 原來他是 match 到這個檔案
The content of modaliases file under this directory will look like this
那這個路徑底下的那個 modaliases，他的內容就是這樣子
Then, it provide....
然後就是說，他下面提供的
For example, in this case, the built-in open source graphic driver is currently in use
像這個情況就是，目前是用 built-in 的 open source 的 graphic driver
Then it suggested that we can use Nvidia driver 470 for this GPU
那他這邊是建議我們可以使用 Nvidia driver 470 來驅動這個 GPU
So, there are modaliases on the hardware
那就是，硬體上面會有這種 modaliases
We can use the content of modaliases to match the hardwares that we want
那我們就可以利用 modaliases 的內容來去 match 到我們想要的硬體
So, practically
那實際上使用起來的話
If you are updating the software, it will actually pop up a dialog called Improved Hardware Support
你如果在軟體更新的時候，他其實會跳出一個叫做 Improved Hardware Support
For example, we use one of the models from Dell Latitude and it will shows up in the updating list
像這邊就是因為他是 Dell Latitude 的這幾個型號，然後他就會出現在更新的清單上面
If you don't want it, you can simply uncheck it
你如果不想要就把他取消打勾就好
The whole user experience will be like this
整個使用者體驗就會是這樣子
So this is basically OEM metapackage
這就是 OEM metapackage
Okay, next we are going to talk about what Concourse CI is
好，那接下來講一下什麼是 Concourse CI?
Concourse CI is an open source tool, mainly used for executing tasks
Concourse CI 他是一個 open source 主要在做執行的一個工具
In fact, it is similar to tools like crontab and cron job
那他其實有時候會有點類似 crontab、cron job 這樣的工具
But it is more.... how do you say it.....Richer, got more settings and more convenient to use
但是他是比較更....怎麼講，更豐富、然後有更多可以設定、跟使用的方便性
It mainly builds the entire pipeline through the "resources, tasks, and jobs"
那他主要是透過裡面的 resources、tasks、跟 jobs
Practically, as you can see
他的那個實際上使用
This is the frame of Concourse CI, the CI provided by default
像這個就是 Concourse CI 他本身的框框，他提供的 CI 給大家看
This is a working set. There is a "resource" here, and the green part is the so-called "job"
他這邊就會運作
Every 30 seconds, the job will be executed as you can see
那他這邊就是每 30 秒會去驅動一次這個 job，大家可以看到
It will be executed every 30 seconds
他就每 30 秒會被驅動一次
How does it achieve this?
那他怎麼辦到的呢？
Every 30 seconds, there will be some changes in the resource
他就是每 30 秒，這個 resource 會有一些改變
And this change will cause the job to be executed
那這個改變，就會去驅動那個 job
This is the basic concept of Concourse CI
這就是他整個使用的概念
And... we can use different combinations of resources
那呃....我們可以用一些 resource 的不同組合
to form some complicated but useful pipelines that meet our needs
可以組出一些非常複雜，但是有符合我們需求的 pipeline 出來
Let's continue
我們繼續往下看
Another point to be mentioned is that it actually has a rather steep learning curve
另外一點要特別提到的是，他其實是會有相當陡峭的學習曲線
Why does Concourse CI officially mention this?
那為什麼他官方會這樣講？
It’s because you actually need a lot of linux concepts in order to master this tool
是因為他裡面其實會有蠻多 linux 的一些觀念你都要會
For example, pipeline in command line, redirect, and etc.
像什麼 pipeline 啊，就是 command line 的 pipeline，然後那些重導
Also you need to be very familiar with some mechanisms of Linux
還有一些比較 linux 這邊運作的一些機制，你要非常的熟悉
You will need those background knowledge in order to master this CI tool
那你要先熟悉這些 background knowlege，才有辦法把這一套 CI 學起來
OK, here are some notes
好，那這邊有一些筆記
Right now, all resources and jobs of Concourse CI are composed by Docker container
目前 Concourse CI 他所有的 resources、jobs 全部都是利用 Docker container 組成、製作出來的
And it currently only supports AMD 64
然後他目前也只支援 AMD 64
Which is the so-called x86_64 architecture
也就是所謂 x86_64 的架構
And its pipeline doesn’t actually support if/else, it just goes all the way to the end
然後他的 pipeline 其實沒有支援 if/else 的分支，他就是一路走到底
It's either right or wrong, either fail or success
他不是對，就是錯 ，不是 fail，就是 success
And you need to be familiar with YAML and JSON syntax
然後你必須要熟悉 YAML 跟 JSON 的語法
In it Help (A Mandarin IT blog), Cang Shi Xian Ye has posted some introductory tutorials
那在 it 邦幫忙這邊， 蒼時弦也有一些入門的教學
There are a few point we need to note: First, Concourse CI is developed by Cloud Foundry
大家可以大概先畫幾個重點出來：Concourse 是由 Cloud Foundry 他們所開發的
They developed this CI/CD tool because all of the existing CI/CD tools can’t solve their problem
就是現有的 CI/CD 工具都沒辦法解決，所以他們才去開發這套 CI/CD 工具
As mentioned earlier, it is just about drawing pipelines
那剛剛前面也有提到，就是他全部都是在畫 pipeline
Use some resources in the pipeline to trigger the execution of the job
用 pipeline 的一些 resource 來驅動 job 去工作
Compared to other CI/CD tools
然後 Concourse CI 跟其他 CI/CD 的工具來比的話
We don't have the concept of plugin in Concourse CI
就是他沒有 plugin 的概念
All its (plugin) extensibility is done through "resources"
他所有的那個擴充性，都是透過 resource 來做的
I'll talk about it later
那等一下會再提到
For me, I made these resource types myself
那像我自己本身就是做了這些 resource type 出來
When I first started using it, I needed to export something in the CI to other places
像一開始使用的時候，發現我可能會需要把 CI 裡面的一些東西，把他存到某個地方去
Concourse CI doesn't provide a built-in tool that can export files
因為 Concourse CI 他本身並沒有提供一個內建可以 export 檔案的工具
It only provides some interfaces and some basic resources
它只有提供 一些介面跟一些基礎的 resource
The built-in resource does not provide storage either
那他 built-in 的 resource 並沒有提供 storage 方面的 resource
Ah, so I made this samba resource and webdav resource
啊 所以我就去做了 samba 的 resource 跟 webdav 的 resource
In addition, sometimes I need to dput JPEG to ppa, this is what the dput resource for
那另外是，接下來這些像 dput 就是我會需要把 JPEG dput 到 ppa 上面
Because I need to dput quite often and it's just repetitive work
那因為這樣的動作其實蠻常在做的，然後一直重複性
So I just made a dput resource to simplify this task
所以我就乾脆弄一個 dput resource 來讓我能夠簡化這樣的工作
There is also a simple autopkgtest resource
那另外也有一個簡單的 autopkgtest resource
Also, we often need to monitor the version of Debian package
那另外就是，我們經常會需要去監測 Debian package version 的版本
For example, when there is a new release of kernel or a new release of GRUB
譬如說 kernel 有新的 release，或是 GRUB 有新的 release
When it detects a change in the version of a package,
會希望能在第一時間，當它偵測到某個 package 的版本有所變化的時候
I want it to do something as soon as possible
馬上去做一些事情
Thus, because of these requirement, I also wrote a resource to monitor change of the Debian package version
所以，因為這樣的需求，所以我也寫了一個 Debian package version 變化偵測的 resource
In addition, I also wrote a mattermost notification myself
那另外就是，我自己也寫了一個 mattermost notification
Because we use mattermost in Canonical
因為 Canonical 有在使用 mattermost
So I use this mattermost notification to send some messages to the mattermost channel
所以就會利用 mattermost notification 把一些訊息傳到 mattermost channel 上面
Also, I need to detect changes in the launchpad bug
那另外是，會去偵測 launchpad bug 的一些變化
Likewise, when there is some changes in launchpad bugs, some jobs will be triggered
然後也是一樣，當那個 launchpad 可能某些 bug 有些變化的話，也會驅動一些工作
And we also use Jenkins
那另外是，因為我們也有用到一些 Jenkins 的東西
So we will need to monitor whether some jobs on Jenkins are triggered
所以會需要去監測 Jenkins 上的某些 job 是否有被驅動
And if Jenkins finishes the task successfully, we can continue to do other things next through Concourse CI
然後如果他有成功的做完事情，那我們就可以接下來做其他事情
Lastly, we also got rclone resource
那另外是 rclone 的 resource
rclone is a more general file copying and syncing tool
rclone 是一個比較通用型的檔案複製跟 sync 的工具
We need to use it, so we made this rclone resource
然後因為有一些需求，所以做了 rclone 的 resource
Okay, let’s introduce the WebDAV resource
好，那這邊來介紹一下就是.....WebDAV 的 resource
The above mentioned WebDAV resource
就是上面這邊有提到的 WebDAV 的 resource
The concept is like this.....
那他使用起來就是像這樣的感覺
I will monitor a file on WebDAV
就是我會去監測一個 WebDAV 上面的檔案
And I will also download the docker image of Ubuntu Focal
然後我也會去把 Ubuntu Focal 的 docker image 抓回來
So the image is ready-to-use in the check-demo-message job
那等一下在 check-demo-message 的 job 可以使用
If there is some files in this demo strorage has changed,
那當這個 demo strorage 裡面的檔案有變化的話
it will triggers this demo message job
他就會去驅動這個 demo message 的 job
This is the content of this pipeline
那這個就是他 pipeline 的內容
First of all, let me define the resource type
首先就是，我先定義一下 resource type
The name is WebDAV, and the type is registry-image
然後他的名稱是 WebDAV，type 是 registry-image
The resource of it is the Webdav resource I put on the github registry in advance
然後他的 source 是我預先先放在 github registry 上面的 Webdav resource
Then I will provide some default values ​​here
然後我這邊給他一些 default 值
For example, my domain is webdav
像我 domain 是 webdav
username and password are also webdav, and then I don't use HTTPS
然後 username、password 也是 webdav，然後我沒有用 HTTPS
Next, I can use this webdav type in the resource
然後，接下來我就可以在 resource 裡面使用這個 webdav 的 type
The name is demo storage, and I also give it an icon
然後他的名稱叫 demo storage，也給他一個 icon
This is the material design icon
這就是 Material design 的 icon
I want it to monitor changes under the demo directory
然後我要他去監測 demo 這個目錄底下的變化
Then the docker image of ubuntu focal
然後接下來是 ubuntu focal 的 docker image
This is the definition of resource
那這就是 resource 這邊的定義
Next I will define job
那我這邊再定義一下 job
I only have one job here called check-demo-message
我這邊只有一個 job 叫 check-demo-message
Its plan is that I am going to download this ubuntu focal image
然後他的 plan  就是我要去抓這個 ubuntu focal 回來
Then I will check the demo storage. If there is any change, it will trigger the job
然後我再去抓那個 demo storage，如果有變化的話就把他 trigger
So here we have a trigger equal to true
那所以這邊會有一個 trigger 等於 true
In other words, if there is any change in the resource of this demo storage,
就是說，當這個 demo storage 的 resource 他有任何的變化的話，
it will automatically trigger the entire job to be executed
他會自動的去 trigger 整個 job 去做事情
The real task we want to achieve lies in here, this task
那真的做事情是在這邊，就是這個 task
And we can define in this task that
然後 task 這邊可以指定說
I want to use the ubuntu focal docker image to build my working environment
我要使用 ubuntu focal 的 docker image 當我的工作環境
And you can define that the platform would be linux
然後你就可以設定說 platform 是 linux
And the input is, I want to directly use the info fetched from this demo storage
然後 input 就是，我要把這個 demo storage 抓到的東西，直接抓進來使用
Then you enter this input. Here is an array, and we would give it a name
那你下這個 input，這邊是一個 array，然後直接給他名稱
Next, you can use command directly in run
那接下來就是，在 run 這邊就可以直接使用 command
path is the name of the command
path 就是 command 的名稱
You can simply cat something and provide a parameter, which is the demo storage message
你就可以直接 cat，然後給他一個參數，就是 demo storage message
Okay, the result will look like this. Let us jump into live demo
好，那他執行起來會長像這樣，那我們來 live demo 一下
I have prepared a repo of the OEM metapackage that I will use later
我這邊有準備一個等一下後面會講到的 OEM metapackage 的 repo
and the git repository
然後 git 的 repository
You can follow the instructions inside and construct this Concourse CI
然後可以按照裡面的說明，就可以把這個 Concourse CI 建構起來
Construct Concourse CI using docker-compose
利用 docker-compose 把他建構起來
OK, I'll login first
好，先登入
After logging in, I can use...
登錄完之後呢，  我就可以用.....
Then, I can say webdav demo pipelines
然後呢，我就可以用 webdav demo pipeplines
Then you can open the link
然後就可以開啟連結
Here we need to wait for a bit
好，這邊要等他一下
This is the first time we built it
他第一次被建立起來
So it takes a while to download the resource image
所以需要一點時間去抓第一次使用的 resource 的 image
Of course it can be reused later on
當然之後就可以重複使用
It finished downloading the resource of webdav
他抓完了 webdav 的 resource
Oh we see, there is a message here
這邊有檢查到，這邊有一個 message
Okay, then its content is to grab a message log
好，那他的內容就是把一個 message log 抓下來
And then print it out
然後把他的內容印出來
It's roughly like this
大概就是這樣子
Because I put it directly in this repo
那因為我這邊是直接放在這個 repo 裡面
So we can also....
那我們也可以啊
For example, add the time I am recording this video to it
比如說，我現在錄這個影片的時間是這個時候
Then you can pass this in again
那可以把東西再傳進去
There is an extra timestamp in the end
後面會多了一個 timestamp 出來
Ok, if it detects a new version, the defined job will be executed automatically
好，他要檢查到一個新的版本，然後他這個 job 就會被自動執行起來
You see there is a timestamp here that I just added
你看這邊就有一個 timestamp 我剛剛加上去的
Well, this is a rough demo of Webdav resource
好，那這個就是大概的一個 demo
Good
好
So how do we use Concourse CI in our OEM metapackages?
那我們是怎麼使用 Concourse CI 在 OEM metapackages 上面呢？
First, we need to mention that
首先要解釋一下，就是 Canonical 的員工
Employees in Canonical will maintain the OEM metapackage
他會去維護 OEM metapackage
under different branches in these 3 git repositories
在這三個 git repository 裡面，不同的 branch 底下
And I will maintain this CI/CD pipeline
然後我會去維護這個 CI/CD pipeline
in this launchpad git repository
在這個 launchpad git repository 上面
Uh, then it will...
呃，然後他會....
For example here, its file name will look like this
像這邊，他檔名就會像這樣子
There will be many branches
會有很多的 branch
Each branch represents a different platform
那每個 branch 就是一個不一樣的平台
The meta CI that I maintain is right here
然後我維護的 meta CI 就是在這邊
So this is relatively simple, it only contains one branch
所以這比較簡單，他只有一個 branch
In addition, I maintain a dashboard, which looks something like this.....
另外是，我有維護一個 dashboard，他的長相大概是這樣
Hmm.... I can come back to explain this dashboard later if we have time
這個，等一下有時間可以再回來解釋一下這個 dashboard
Okay, actually the execution result of Concourse CI will be like this
好，那實際上 Concourse CI 執行起來會像這樣
It will have multiple jobs, and all are all triggered by git branched
他會有很多 job，然後都是由 git 的 branch 去驅動
After it finishes somthing, if it fails.....
然後他做完事情，他會透過 mattermost
Some messages will be sent to the mattermost channel through mattermost
如果失敗的話，會透過 mattermost 去傳遞一些訊息到 mattermost channel
The dashboard mentioned before looks like this
那剛剛提到的 dashboard 長得像這樣
Actually, here, this autopkg boostrap build pass, real build pass
其實這邊，像這個 autopkg boostrap build pass、real build pass
Each actually matches to a certain job here
他其實就是對應到這裡的某一個 job
For example, this modaliases build pass, it will match to this modaliases
像這個 modaliases build pass，他就會對應到這個 modaliases
And there is the installation of boostrap down here
那這裡有 boostrap 的 install 會在這邊，最下面這裡
kernel flavour will lies here
kernel flavour 會在這裡
then the market name will be here
然後 market name 會在這裡
It's basically like this
大概是醬
Okay, that's basically....
好，那基本上就是....
I have another pipeline job to check these three git repositories regularly
我有另外準備一個 pipeline 的 job，去定時檢查這三個 git repository
If there is any new branches
啊如果他有任何的新的 branch 的話
Or if some branch is deleted, it will update the meta ci that I maintain
或者他刪掉 branch ，都會去更新我自己維護的這個 meta ci
Automatically update it
自動去更新
All I need to do is actually to edit these two templates
然後我所需要做的事情其實就是去改變這兩個 template
And add some more test datasets
然後增加一些更多的測試
Let's jump into live demo
那我們來實際的 live demo 一下
Refer to readme, it mentioned that we can set a reconfigure ci
參考 readme，這邊提到可以直接設定一個 reconfigure 的 ci
And it will automatically watch the meta ci repository
然後他就會自動去 watch 這個 meta ci 的 repository
If there is any change, it will then automatically build individual CI
然後當他有任何的變化的時候，他會再自動去把個別的 CI 建立起來
We can unpalse this and it will start to operate
那我們可以把他 unpalse 一下，他就開始運作了
Here we should improved it by not running five jobs at the same time
這邊應該改善一下，不要讓他同時跑五個 job
We should run one job at a time, one at a time
應該讓他輪流，一個一個跑
So that we can prevent resource contention and slow execution when running multiple jobs at the same time
要不然他一次同時跑會讓 resource 搶來搶去，反而讓執行變慢
All done!
全部好了！
OK, that basically looks like this
好，那大概看起來就像這樣
So why we see nothing here?
那為什麼這邊會看到整個黑黑的
Because there are too many jobs in it,
是因為它裡面的 job 太多了
it is unable to display everything LOL
所以就沒有辦法顯示（笑～
But you can click to see
不過可以點進去看
For example, the vary-..... mentioned in the presentation, the one begins with v
像在簡報裡面提到的這個 vary，v 開頭的
It will solve the problem that it won’t check automatically
那這解決他不會自動去檢查
I wrote a small program to catch the webhook of the function
我是透過 Concourse CI 他提供的 webhook
through the the webhook provided by Concourse CI
另外寫一個小程式去接那個 function 配的 webhook
It’s coming in here, and then it trigger this
這邊傳進來，然後再去驅動這邊
If you want to use it, you can just trigger it manually
這邊如果要使用的話，就是手動的去 trigger 就好
After checking it will look something like this
他就是，檢查之後就是長得像這樣
Then it will start to do some of these pre-defined tests
然後就會開始做這些事先定義好的一些測試
This is basically.....
那這大概就是
how we integrate Concourse CI with our OEM metapackages
我們怎麼樣使用 Concourse CI 在 OEM metapackages 上面
Oh and because the computer I am using for this demo is actually quite...
喔因為我做 demo 的這臺電腦，其實是是蠻....
The computer I am using is actually not that powerful
資源是沒有那麼 powerful
So yes, the execution would be slower
所以會，執行比較慢
If you list every task out
如果把他全部都列出來的話
The list will become very long because there are too many jobs
他會因為 job 太多就會變得很長
That’s why we order it alphabetically
所以才用字母來排序
Hopefully it will be faster
反應會快一點
Also... Let 's run this first
另外是....這個先讓他跑一下
Hmmm.... Let's demonstrate the next thing
像....接下來就來示範一下
For example, you can see that there are already some test jobs here
譬如說你看現在這邊已經有這些測試的 job
Now I will add a new test job
那我現在來新增一個新的測試的 job
All I need to do is to modify this yaml called project template
我就只需要直接去修改一個叫做 project template 的 yaml
And we'll see...
然後我們看....
Let's do a random check or something
隨便做一個檢查之類的
Oh, let's write a job to print out modaliases
不然我來做一個 job 去把 modaliases 印出來好了
Just copy the existing one here
那直接複製這邊現有的
Then here we will get Ubuntu request, get OEM
然後這邊會 get Ubuntu request、get OEM
Here is check originally, we want to change it to print
這是 check，要把它改成 print
Then check modaliases
然後 check modaliases
I will just copy this
我就把他隨便複製
Okay, here you can change it to...
好，然後這裡你就改成.....
Okay, I just added a new test job
好，我這邊就直接加了一個新的測試
Called print-modaliases
叫做 print-modaliases
Just print it out.....
就是直接把它印出來
print out the modaliases string
把 modaliases string 印出來
It will input the Ubuntu branch of the current platform,
他這邊會去把 Ubuntu
to this Ubuntu path
這個 platform 的 Ubuntu branch，input 到 Ubuntu 的這個 path
And here is the OEM branch
那這邊是 OEM 的 branch
It will be added to the OEM folder
會 input 到 OEM 的 folder 底下
Then you should be able to cat it out in this print-modaliases
然後在 print-modaliases 這邊就可以直接把他 cat 出來
This should work
應該就可以了
We added this
加了這個
and defined a function
然後定義了一個 function
This ytt here, I can explain it later
就是這個 ytt，等一下可以再解釋一下
Then I wrote a new job
然後直接就寫了一個新的 job
The content is basically like this
內容大概是這樣
Then I can do generate
然後我就可以用 generate
What is generate?
generate 是什麼？
By doing generate, it will read the template
generate 他會去讀 template
and export 3 projects, which are somerville, stella, and sutton
然後幫這個 somerville stella sutton 這三個專案都把它轉出來
Then it will use the tool, ytt, to generate a YAML file for the final platform
然後再利用 ytt 這個工具去把他產生最後的 platform 的 YAML 檔案
It will generate somerville.yaml, stella.yaml, and sutton.yaml
就是產生 somerville.yaml stella.yaml 跟 sutton.yaml
Let's test it~
執行一下～
So I use command line
然後我就直接透過 command 的方式
to generate the above mentioned somerville....
把剛剛 gen 出來的 somerville.....
Also pass in the mattermost webhook
mattermost 的 hook 也要給他一下
Hmm probably ytt does not support dash
可能是 ytt 這邊沒有支援
Alright
好，沒錯
Wait a second ? ! Maybe we should add group into it
咦？！不然我們把 group 加上去
Let's modify again
再改一下
Great
好
Then you can see that there is a new test job called varys-focal-modaliases-print
然後可以看到這邊就多了一個 varys-focal-modaliases-print 新的測試的 job
Of course it will execute every jobs for me, so I just need to change one thing
那當然他每一個都會幫我做完，所以我只要改一個地方就好
Okay, here is the modaliases-print I just added
像這邊就是我剛剛加的 modaliases print
A brand new job
一個新的 job
So suppose it is another new test
假設他是另外一個新的
that we needed to test the OEM metapackage.
可能需要對 OEM metapackage 做測試的一個新的測試
That is how we can add it into our pipeline
那就是可以利用這樣的方式把他加進來
Great
好
So this is the end of my sharing, hope you guys will like it
那以上就是我的分享
Okay, thank you everyone~
好，謝謝大家～